<resources xmlns:tools="http://schemas.android.com/tools">
    <string name="app_name">Better at Chess</string>

    <string name="native_ad_unit_id">ffdf4cd43261d7ec</string>
    <string name="interstitial_ad_unit_id">bf8c92edb761d797</string>

    <string name="Tip1" >The Najdorf begins: 1. e4 c5 2. Nf3 d6 3. d4 cxd4 4. Nxd4 Nf6 5. Nc3 a6 Blacks 5…a6 aims to deny the b5 square to Whites knights and light square bishop while maintaining flexible development. If Black plays 5…e5?! immediately, then after 6.Bb5+! Bd7 (or 6…Nbd7 7.Nf5) 7.Bxd7+ Nbxd7 (or Qxd7) 8.Nf5, the knight on f5 is difficult to dislodge without concessions. Games in the Najdorf frequently feature opposite side castling, where White castles long and both sides launch simultaneous attacks on their opponents kings.  Black usually plans a queen side minority attack to pressure Whites e4 pawn. This is often carried out by means of …b5, …Bb7, and placing a knight on d5, or c4 via b6. the best position would look like the above board.</string>
    <string name="Tip2" >The Berlin Wall is a very good defense for Black in the Ruy Lopez (Spanish). This tough sideline is played by grandmasters at top level chess events. It was also used in the world chess championship 2014 by Viswanathan Anand.  Black does not play a6 but plays Nf6 instead  1.e4 e5 2.Nf3 Nc6 3.Bb5 Nf6  Often in the Ruy Lopez, white does not want to defend the e–pawn with Nc3 or d3. This is because white often wants to play an early c2 c3 and d2 d4, fighting for a central space advantage.  Because of this, white often reacts to …Nf6 by simply castling. White can play Re1 next turn to defend the e4 pawn, and if black plays …Nxe4, then black could be in danger of the center opening up before black gets castled.  Let’s translate these words to concrete moves. After 4. 0 0 Nxe4 5. d4, white is threatening to open the center before black can castle.  Black’s point in the Berlin Defense is revealed with 5…Nd6  Now we see why black did not kick the bishop away from the b5 square! The knight escapes any e file pins, while also gaining a tempo by attacking this bishop.  If white wants to win their pawn back, the most logical way to do so is to exchange this bishop off for the knight, and then take on e5.  After 6. Bxc6 dxc6 7. dxe5 Nf5, white even gets to prevent black from castling with 8. Qxd8+ Kxd8  This is the famous “Berlin Endgame.” Optically, white looks better. Black’s king is stuck in the center. Furthermore, white has a healthy 4 on 3 pawn majority on the king side, whereas black’s queenside majority is crippled because of the doubled c pawns.  In a pure king and pawn endgame, this turns out to be a winning advantage for white – but getting there is no easy task! In the meantime, black has the two bishops in an open position, which is a significant advantage.</string>
    <string name="Tip3" tools:ignore="Typos">The starting position of the Queen’s Indian Defense is reached after 1.d4 Nf6 2.c4 e6 3.Nf3 b6  The main battle in this chess opening revolves around control of the critical e4 and d5 squares. Black seeks to control these squares with a knight on f6 and a bishop on b7.  Controlling these squares can include occupying them with pieces and playing moves like …Ne4.  Also, keep in mind that in the Queen’s Indian Defense, instead of …Bb7, the bishop is often developed to a6. From a6, the bishop puts pressure on the c4 pawn. This is particularly effective if White chooses to play the fianchetto variation ith g3 and Bg2.  White chooses 3.Nf3 instead of 3.Nc3 to avoid the pin after 3…Bb4. There is obviously nothing wrong with a natural developing move like 3.Nf3 and Nc3 can be played later.  The Fianchetto Variation With 6…Bb4+  1.d4 Nf6 2.c4 e6 3.Nf3 b6 4.g3 Ba6 5.b3 Bb7 6.Bg2 Bb4+  the line goes : 1.d4 Nf6 2.c4 e6 3.Nf3 b6 4.g3 Ba6 5.b3 Bb7 6.Bg2 Bb4+  Black played 4…Ba6 to tempt White into defending the c4 pawn with b3. Once black achieved that goal, the bishop moved back to the long diagonal to challenge the white bishop on the long diagonal.  After 6…Bb4+ white has little choice but to play 7.Bb2 when black responds with 7…a5. The idea is to gain control of the a file and prevent Nc3 if white plays Bxb4.  7.Bd2 a5 8.0 0 0 0 9.Qc2 d6 10Nc3 Nbd7 11.Rxfe1  The c2 square is a natural square for the white queen because the queen helps support e4, and when white plays Rfe1, the intention to play e4is quite clear.  Black must remember a two move combination to prevent e4 – Bxc3 and Be4. Once the queen moves away and no longer supports e4, the black bishop can return to b7.  Ivanchuk sacrificed the exchange in this game while playing the Queen’s Indian Defense against a strong opponent rated over 2700 Elo.  Queen’s Indian Defense against a strong opponent rated over 2700 Elo.  Openings don’t need to start razor sharp to be effective or lead to exciting play. The Queen’s Indian Defense can lead to attacking play even with a solid positional character.  Since the hallmark of a good chess opening is to help you reach playable middlegames, the Queen’s Indian Defense ranks as one of the best chess openings.  There is no need to worry about getting caught in a trap early in the game, and there is not a lot of theory to learn. The Queen’s Indian Defense will take you quietly to an equal position in the middlegame without any trouble at all.</string>
    <string name="Tip4" >The Kan Variation is a flexible and solid option for Black.  By playing a6 early, Black prevents an immediate Nb5 from White, while also preparing to expand on the queen side with b5.  This variation often leads to a more positional game, with each player trying to control the key central squares.  the line goes : e4 c5 2.Nf3 e6 3.d4 cxd4 4.Nxd4 a6  The Paulsen Variation, initiated with 1.e4 c5 2.Nf3 e6, is a flexible and solid choice, providing options to transition into many other Sicilian lines. The Paulsen often leads to complex middle game positions where strategic understanding is pivotal.  As you explore the Sicilian Defense and its many variations, remember that choosing a variation should align with your style of play and strategic preferences. Take your time to understand the different ideas in each variation and, most importantly, enjoy the process of learning and playing the Sicilian Defense</string>
    <string name="Tip5" tools:ignore="Typos">The Nimzo Indian Defense is a Queen’s Pawn Opening beginning with 1. d4 Nf6 2. c4 e6 3. Nc3 Bb4  Nimzo Indian Defense  With their third move, black pins the white knight to the king, preventing white from expanding immediately in the center with e4 and threatening to double white’s pawns!  Both sides have a wide variety of options from this starting position, making the Nimzo Indian Defense one of the most strategically complex openings in all of chess!  first, let’s briefly discuss a move–order issue that every Nimzo Indian Defense player must understand:  3. Nf3 – White Avoids the Nimzo Indian Defense  Anti Nimzo Indian To avoid allowing black to pin the knight, some players will play 3. Nf3 or 3. g3 with white. The bad news is that it’s not possible to play the Nimzo Indian Defense against this set up  there is no knight to pin!  The good news from blacks perspective, however, is that this set up from white is less ambitious in a sense. By not playing 3. Nc3, white is no longer threatening to play e4 next turn and take the full center.  Most Nimzo Indian Defense players will handle this line by playing either 3…Bb4+ (The Bogo Indian Defense) aiming for a Nimzo Indian style setup even without the knight on c3, or 3…b6 (The Queen’s Indian Defense), adding even more control to the critical e4 square by allowing the light squared bishop to help!  But the focus of this article will be the Nimzo Indian…so let’s get into it!  4. a3  a3 Nimzo Indian  This move isn’t too popular these days, but the resulting positions are a good illustration of each side’s ideas in the Nimzo Indian. White forces black’s hand and ensures that the dark bishop will be traded off.  After 4…Bxc3+ 5. bxc3, 5…c5 is black’s most popular option.  Nimzo Indian a3 Main line  This move is quite instructive. Black will often put their central pawns on dark squares in the Nimzo Indian, after exchanging off their dark bishop. This pawn “freezes” the doubled pawns on the c file.  Black isn’t worried about white taking this “free” pawn – white would then have trippled, isolated pawns on the c file and is sure to lose some material back! /n The game may continue 6. e3 Nc6 7. Bd3 0 0 8. Ne2 b6 9. e4 Ne8 (this knight often heads to d6, adding to the pressure against the weak c4 pawn!) 10. f4 f5 (the other point of the knight retreat, black wants to stop white from steamrolling them on the kingside). 12. Ng3 g6  Typical Nimzo  Both sides are fighting hard to impose their will on the position! Black created a weakness on c4 in the opening by doubling white’s pawns, and is ready to ramp up the pressure with moves like …Nd6 and …Na5. White has the bishop pair as compensation, and took a lot of space on the center and kingside.  The result is a roughly equal position – but it’s good to know the key ideas to implement in case your opponent goes wrong! It’s easy to imagine an informed player with white playing nonchalant developing moves, for instance, as their c4 pawn is surrounded and destroyed after …Ba6, …Nc6 a5, and …Ne8 d6.  4. f3  f3 Nimzo  This is a very direct way to play against the Nimzo Indian Defense. White renews the threat to play e4 and grab the full center!  Black can still play …c5 here (covered in the video above), but against this particular move, it makes a lot of sense to switch back to a “Queen’s Gambit style” pawn structure with 4…d5.  Black clamps down harder on the e4 square. If black can prevent white from playing e4, then white will likely regret playing f3 – it takes away the knight’s best square!  One continuation is 5. a3 Bxc3+ 6. bxc3 c5 7. cxd5 exd5 8. e3 0 0  f3 Nimzo Main Line  White manages to exchange off one of their doubled pawns in this line, but white is behind in development. Black has scored well in recent grandmaster games from this position.  4. Qc2  Qc2 Nimzo Indian  I’ll put one more line in the spotlight to conclude this article. The 4. Qc2 system has become very popular against the Nimzo Indian, and it’s easy to see why. Not only does the queen prevent black from doubling white’s pawns, but it also watches over the e4 square!  Black has many ways to play. 4…0 0 is possible, but black can also continue with 4…c5 as we’ve seen in some other continuations. Here, white often plays 5. dxc5  exchange line nimzo  Now the black bishop will likely have to take on c5, rather than on c3, leading to a different sort of position than those we’ve seen so far. Yet another example of the wide variety of positions the Nimzo Indian Defense can yield!  After 5…0 0 6. a3 Bxc5 7. Nf3 b6 8. Bf4 Bb7 9. Rd1 Nc6 10. e3:  Kasparov Nimzo Indian  Black can seek play on the kingside after 10..Nh5 11. Bg3 f5  Conclusion  The Nimzo Indian Defense is a fascinating opening to study because of the multitude of possibilities that each side has. Black can strike at the center with …c5, …d5, or both, depending on the continuation. Sometimes white obtains the bishop pair (after …Bxc3), and sometimes black ends up with the pair of bishops, albeit less frequently!</string>
    <string name="Tip6" >The Nimzowitsch–Larsen Attack (also known as the Nimzo Larsen Attack, Larsen s Opening and Queens Fianchetto Opening) is a chess opening typically starting with the move: 1.b3 but sometimes introduced by the move order 1.Nf3 and then 2.b3. The flank opening move 1.b3 prepares to fianchetto the queens bishop where it will help control the central squares in hypermodern fashion and put pressure on Blacks kingside.  Aron Nimzowitsch (1886 – 1935) and Bent Larsen (1935 2010) are the two players whose names adorn the variation. Both were noted for their individual style of play and free thinking. Nimzowitsch was born in Riga but eventually relocated to Denmark. Larsen (featured in yesterday’s instalment of Checkmate Monday) was born in Denmark, the same year Nimzowitsch died. Both players used the opening extensively (but not exclusively), although Nimzowitsch usually preferred to preface b2 b3 with 1.Nf3.  The opening can be played in various different ways. Some players will stick to the dark squared strategy with Bb2, e3, Bb5, f4, Nf3 and Ne5 (which transposes to lines from the Bird’s Opening, 1.f4) and others will prefer to utilise a double fianchetto with a subsequent g3 and Bg2. Transpositions to the English Opening (1.c4) are entirely possible too. Yet another approach is to head directly into reverse Sicilian structures, as used by Bobby Fischer in one of the games featured below.  Given the sheer amount of potential plans arising from 1.b3, it is easy to see the appeal for players who prefer not to spend their lives shackled to cast iron opening theory. There are lots of surprises just waiting to be sprung upon unsuspecting opponents. Here, for example, is a creative idea as early as the third move.  1.b3 Nf6  2.Bb2 g6  The King’s Indian approach often acts as a panacea for Black against a whole range of non theoretical openings. Here, Black may not be familiar with a g pawn jab by White.  3.g4  1.b3 Nf6 2.Bb2 g6 3.g4  Black needs to think very carefully how best to react to this move. After 3…Bg7 4.g5 Nh5 5.Bxg7 Nxg7 6.Qc1 the queen will replace the bishop on the long diagonal and White will quickly castle on the queenside. It will not be so easy for Black to acclimatize to such an unusual position.</string>
    <string name="Tip7" >The Hedgehog is a pawn formation in chess adopted usually by Black that can arise from several openings. Black exchanges the pawn on c5 for Whites pawn on d4, and then places pawns on the squares a6, b6, d6, and e6. These pawns form a row of spines behind which Black develops their forces. Typically, the bishops are placed on b7 and e7, knights on d7 and f6, queen on c7, and rooks on c8 and e8 (or c8 and d8). Although Blacks position is cramped, it has great latent energy, which may be released if Black is able to play …b5 or …d5 at some point. These pawn breaks are particularly effective because White usually places pawns on c4 and e4 (the Maróczy Bind).  Black manoeuvring  Once the basic Hedgehog structure is in place, and depending on how White responds, Black has various ways of reorganizing their pieces. The knight on d7 often hops to c5, where it attacks a white pawn on e4; or to e5, where it attacks a pawn on c4. The knight on f6 can go to e8 (when Black placed their rook on d8) to defend the d6 pawn, or to d7 or even to h5, if unoccupied. The black queen can be moved to b8 (unmasking the rook on c8 and perhaps supporting …b5) or a8 (eyeing d5). A rook placed on d8 serves to defend the d6 pawn and support its push to d5. Sometimes Black plays …Bf8, …g6, and …Bg7 (or more simply …Bf6 if f6 is vacant) to exert some influence over d4. Or the same bishop can be brought to c7 (via d8) to target Whites kingside (in conjunction with a queen on b8). There are also situations where Black can create a kingside attack, by playing …Kh8, …Rg8, and …g5, often followed by doubling rooks on the g file and pushing the g pawn to g4.  Traditional chess strategy would have frowned upon Blacks setup, since their pieces have little room in which to manoeuvre. In the early 1970s, hedgehog was a generic term for any setup that was cramped, defensive and difficult to attack, but today refers specifically to this formation. The Hedgehog first became extensively analysed in the 1970s, when players began to appreciate the rich variety of strategic ideas that arose from it. While Blacks position is cramped, it is also relatively free of weaknesses. There is no obvious way for White to attack Blacks pawn structure, but as outlined above, Black has several methods at their disposal for creating counterplay. Thus the Hedgehog has retained its popularity as a system of development in modern praxis.</string>
    <string name="Tip8" >Alekhine s Defence is a chess opening that begins with the moves:  1. e4 Nf6  Black tempts Whites pawns forward to form a broad pawn centre, with plans to undermine and attack the white structure later in the spirit of hypermodern defence. Whites imposing mass of pawns in the centre often includes pawns on c4, d4, e5, and f4. Grandmaster (GM) Nick de Firmian observes of Alekhines Defence in MCO–15 (2008), The game immediately loses any sense of symmetry or balance, which makes the opening a good choice for aggressive fighting players.  The opening is named after Alexander Alekhine, who introduced it in the 1921 Budapest tournament in games against Endre Steiner and Fritz Sämisch.In addition to Alekhine, another early exponent of the defence was Ernst Grunfeld.  After the usual 2.e5 Nd5, three main variations of Alekhines Defence use 3.d4, but there are other options for White at this point. Two of the main lines are the Exchange Variation and the Four Pawns Attack. The Exchange Variation continues 3.d4 d6 4.c4 Nb6 5.exd6. White has some space advantage. Black can capitalise on the half–open centre with …g6, …Bg7 with …Bg4 eventually being played. The Four Pawns Attack continues 3.d4 d6 4.c4 Nb6 5.f4. White has a somewhat larger space advantage though the centre is not fixed. Black has a number of options. Black can play …Qd7 with …0–0 0 and …f6 putting pressure on Whites d pawn. Black can play …Nb4 with …c5 hoping to exchange the d pawn. Finally, Black can play …Be7 with …0 0 and …f6 attacking the centre. Minor variations include OSullivans Gambit, 3.d4 b5 (intending 4.Bxb5 c5 5.dxc5?? Qa5+), and 3.d4 d6 4.Bc4, the Balogh Variation.  All in all, the provocative approach taken by black in the Alekhine Defense is considered somewhat dubious by most elite chess players, and I personally don’t know of any Master who uses the Alekhine as their main weapon against the King’s Pawn Opening. White has many ways to get a quite pleasant position against it.  That said, Alekhine Defense specialists can be found at the club level across the world, and even the pros bust it out on occasion as a surprise! If you’re up to the challenge and don’t mind being a little cramped, give the Alekhine Defense a try.</string>
    <string name="Tip9" >Larsen’s Opening is a hypermodern opening, meaning that control of the center is exerted by pieces rather than central pawn control (e.g 1.e4 or 1.d4). It begins after a 1.b3, which prepares a queen side fianchetto.  The opening is named after Danish Grandmaster Bent Larsen, who was inspired by chess player and theoretician Aron Nimzowitsch. As such, it also bears the name the Nimzowitsch–Larsen Attack or the Nimzo Larsen Attack.  Larsen initially had great success in the opening in his heyday of the 1960s. The opening fell out of favor after the 1970 USSR vs. Rest of the World Match when Larsen played it against then World Champion Boris Spassky and lost in 17 moves.  Bobby Fischer used the opening on a handful of occasions and won all five games he used it  in 1970. Top players today occasionally employ the opening, including Hikaru Nakamura and Richard Rapport.  Black has two main responses to 1.b3, them being 1.d5 and 1.e5.  The Classical Variation 1…d5 It makes sense for Black to play this or 1…e5 to occupy the center with pawns.  2.Bb2  The Natural continuation for White as they were planning to fianchetto this bishop. White plans to put pressure on the g7 square and this move does that.  2…c5  Black is planning to play d4 if they get a chance and blunt the bishop’s target on g7. In this line, the d4 square is crucial and both sides will be fighting for control of it.  3.e3 Nc6 4.Bb5  What if instead of 3…Nc6 Black plays 3…a6 to prevent the White from playing Bb5 and pinning the knight on c6?  White can play 4.f4 to clamp down on the e5 square, 4…Nc6 5.Nf3 Nf6 6.Be2 e6 7. 0 0 Be7 8.Ne5 Qc7 9.d3 0 0 10.Nd2 Nd7 11.Ndf3  White has completed development without letting d4 happen and still holds a firm grip on the a1 h8 diagonal.  White’s queen will usually go to e1 and then head up to g3 to exert pressure on the g7 square.  4…e6 5.f4, again clamping down on the e5 square. …Nf6 6.Nf3 Bd7 7.0 0  The move order here is quite important actually. For example, if instead 7.d3, …Qa5+ 8.Nc3 d4 1. 9.exd4 cxd4 10.Bxc6 Bxc6 11.Nxd4 Bxg2, and Black is much better off.  7…Be7  White will eventually take the knight on c6 as their light squared bishop does not really have anywhere to go. From here the plan will be to maneuver the queen to g3 and exert pressure on g7.  Larsen’s opening is an opening full of potential and attack for White. It is an opening that is likely to take your opponents out of prep, so this is an added value for White. That said, Black can develop in a very flexible manner, and can choose the type of set up they like. Because it is a flank opening, black is free to establish their pawns in the center.  All in all, exciting games arise from this opening. It is a sound opening with good chances for both sides.</string>
    <string name="Tip10" >The Marshall Attack (also called the Marshall Gambit) is a chess opening characterised by the moves:  1. e4 e5  2. Nf3 Nc6  3. Bb5 a6  4. Ba4 Nf6  5. O O Be7  6. Re1 b5  7. Bb3 O O  8. c3 d5  The Marshall Attack is an aggressive line in the Ruy Lopez, where Black sacrifices a pawn by playing d5 to gain initiative and a king side attack. Frank Marshall famously debuted it in his game against José Raúl Capablanca in 1918.[1] Although Marshall lost the game, the opening gained popularity and was adopted by many top players, still seeing use today at the top level by players such as Levon Aronian and Ding Liren. It is of particular theoretical importance as a way for Black to play actively and avoid the so called Spanish Torture of the Closed Ruy Lopez. Moreover, it has led to the development of several "Anti Marshall" lines designed to avoid its complications.After the main continuation to Blacks pawn sacrifice, 9. exd5 Nxd5 10. Nxe5 Nxe5 11. Rxe5 c6 12. d4 Bd6 13. Re1, Whites king side has lost an important defender in the f3 knight and Black can start a powerful attack against the White king with 13… Qh4. White also suffers from an under developed queen side and faces some difficulties developing its remaining knight since the pawn on c3 blocks one of its squares. However, White may reach an endgame with a pawn advantage if able to withstand Blacks attack.</string>
    <string name="page1"> Get better at chess is an easy guide to understand the openings that you can play and react to, the first move in a chess game are crucial … so mastering have fun learning those openings and crushing at chess </string>
    <string name="page1btn"> CHESS OPENINGS</string>
    <string name="logo"> Better at chess logo </string>
    <string name="Title_1">Najdorf</string>
    <string name="Title_2">Berlin Wall</string>
    <string name="Title_3">Queens Indian</string>
    <string name="Title_4">Kan Sicilian or Paulsen Sicilian</string>
    <string name="Title_5">Nimzo Indian</string>
    <string name="Title_6">Nimzo Larsen attack   1.Nf3</string>
    <string name="Title_7">Hedgehog variation</string>
    <string name="Title_8">Alekhine Defense</string>
    <string name="Title_9">Nimzo Larsen</string>
    <string name="Title_10">Marshall Attack of the Ruy Lopez</string>
</resources>